A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30 FA302
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
1922-1982
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Harkness, Edward Stephen
Harkness, Charles W.
Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman
Commonwealth Fund
Harkness, Anna M. Richardson
FA302
8.56 Cubic Feet 20 document boxes.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research.
Requests to View Commonwealth Fund Reference Files
All requests to view Reference Files are to be made by Box Number. Retrieval of individual folders is not permitted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by subject or by individuals' last name.
Scope and Contents
The Reference Files consist of ready-reference materials, primarily publications and articles, orginally compiled for the Commonwealth Fund Library.
The dates indicated for published material are often the stamped date at which the item was accepted into the Commonwealth Fund Library collection, rather than the date of publication.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accession 1986:069.
United States; War relief; Child psychology; Child mental health; Education, Rural; Child welfare; Public health; Public welfare; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Medical education; Medical research; Medicine, Rural; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Hygiene; Law; Legal issues; Legal research; Mental health; Harkness, Edward Stephen; Social Science Research Council; Harvard University; Harkness, Charles W.; Phillips Exeter Academy; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Yale University; Commonwealth Fund; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Columbia University
- Aldrich, Malcolm P., 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American Assembly, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- American University of Beirut, 1949-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Association of American Medical Colleges: Grant Material, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- B (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Barr, David (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Boston University School of Medicine, Home Care Program (Box 2, Folder 7)
- C (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Child Research Council of Denver, 1929-1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Chronic Illness Newsletter, 1951-1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Cornell University/New York Hospital, 1951-1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Education Research (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Fellowships and Scholarships, Dr. Heffron's Survey 1956-1957, 1953-1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Foundations: General, 1951-1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Foundations: General, 1955-1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Foundations: General, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Foundations: Investigation (Congressional)
  - Patman Committee 1962, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Reports, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Reports, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, 1952-1955 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Freud, Sigmund, 1952-1955 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Fry, C.C., 1951 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Fullbright Program, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Galdston, Iago, 1949-1957 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Ganong, William F., 1958-1965 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Gardner, John W., 1965 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Genest, Jacques, 1955-1958 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Glueck, Sheldon, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Group for the Advancement of Psychiatry: Reports, 1962-1972 (Box 6, Folder 31-32, Box 5, Folder 29-30)
- H, 1955-1964 (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Harkness Edward S.
  - Clippings
    - 1928-1931 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - 1932-1937 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - 1938-1957 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Obituary, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Inquiries Regarding, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 38)
- Harkness, E.S., Mrs., 1940-1948 (Box 7, Folder 39)
- Harkness Estate, 1941-1982 (Box 7, Folder 40)
- Harkness House, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 41)
- Harkness, Mary S.: Obituary, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 42)
- Harvard University Medical School, 1961-1963 (Box 7, Folder 43)
- Hoover, Herbert, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 44)
- Hospital Survey and Construction Act, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 45)
- Hunterdon Medical College, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 46)
- Kohler, Wolfgang, 1952-1956 (Box 8, Folder 47)
- Kris, Ernst, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 48)
- L, 1953-1959 (Box 8, Folder 49)
- M, 1953-1973 (Box 8, Folder 50)
- Medical Education
  - 1930-1949 (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - 1954-1959 (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - 1960-1962 (Box 10, Folder 55)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 56)
  - Medical Education in Arizona, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 57)
  - Medical Education in Australia (Box 11, Folder 58)
  - Clippings (Box 11, Folder 59)
  - Conference on Evaluation Studies in Medical Education, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 60)
  - Financial Assistance, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 61)
  - Graduate, 1953-1958 (Box 12, Folder 62)
  - Graduate: Foreign, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 63)
  - Medical Education in Great Britian, 1960-1963 (Box 12, Folder 64)
  - International, 1962-1966 (Box 13, Folder 66)
  - Internship, 1950-1965 (Box 12, Folder 65)
  - Medical Education in Louisiana, 1955 (Box 13, Folder 67)
  - Medical Education in Mississippi, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 68)
  - Medical Education in New Jersey, 1951-1964 (Box 13, Folder 69)
- Medical Services for the Aged: Clippings (Box 14, Folder 70)
- Mehl, John W., 1960 (Box 14, Folder 71)
- Melzack, Ronald, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 72)
- Mental Hygiene in Massachusetts, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 73)
- Miller, George E., 1962 (Box 14, Folder 74)
- Miscellaneous, 1965-1977 (Box 14, Folder 75)
- Motulsky, A.G., 1950-1959 (Box 14, Folder 76)
- Murphy, Douglas, 1955-1965 (Box 14, Folder 77)
- Museum of the City of New York, 1953-1962 (Box 14, Folder 78)
- National Academy of Sciences and National Research Council, 1965-1976 (Box 14, Folder 79)
- National Bureau of Economic Research, 1959-1973 (Box 14, Folder 80)
- National Commission on Community Health Services: Health Manpower (Action to Meet Community Needs), 1967-1970 (Box 14, Folder 81)
- National Commission on Community Health Services, Inc., 1965-1966 (Box 15, Folder 82)
- New York State: Governor's Steering Committee on Social Problems (Box 15, Folder 83)
- Obituaries
  - A-K (Box 16, Folder 84)
  - L-Z (Box 16, Folder 85)
- Oliver, Jean, 1954 (Box 16, Folder 86)
- Opler, Marvin K., 1956-1957 (Box 16, Folder 87)
- Personals
  - A-F (Box 16, Folder 88)
  - G-L (Box 16, Box 89)
  - M-R (Box 16, Folder 90)
  - S-Z (Box 16, Folder 91)
- Pilgrim Trust, 1930-1948 (Box 16, Folder 92)
- Programmed Instruction, 1964-1965 (Box 17, Folder 93)
- Rappleye, Willard C., 1944-1965 (Box 17, Folder 94)
- Rip Van Winkle Clinic, 1953-1962 (Box 17, Folder 95)
- Rochester Regional Hospital Plan (New York), 1954 (Box 17, Folder 96)
- Salzburg Seminar, 1954-1972 (Box 17, Folder 97)
- Senn, Milton J., 1965 (Box 17, Folder 98)
- Shands, Harley C., 1958 (Box 17, Folder 99)
- Smith, Barry C.: Papers read before conference, 1922-1940 (Box 18, Folder 100)
- Social Security, 1965-1969 (Box 18, Folder 101)
- State University of New York: Downstate Medical Center, 1947-1950 (Box 18, Folder 102)
- Swank, Roy L., 1953-1958 (Box 18, Folder 103)
- Tennessee State Medical Association, 1950-1953 (Box 18, Folder 104)
- Teacher Report, 1948 (Box 18, Folder 105)
- Tributes, 1945-1979; bulk
  - A-D (Box 19, Folder 106)
  - E-H (Box 19, Folder 107)
  - J-M (Box 19, Folder 108)
  - O-Z (Box 19, Folder 109)
- United States Congress
  - Bills, Messages, etc., 1965-1974 (Box 19, Folder 110)
  - Bills, etc., 1965-1966 (Box 19, Folder 111)
  - Bills and Reports, 1961-1967 (Box 20, Folder 113, Folder 112)
  - Laws, 1965-1967 (Box 20, Folder 114)